Butler mss., 1835-1937 LMC 1177
Lilly Library
Butler mss.
1835-1937
Lilly Library
Butler, Amos W. 1860-1937.
LMC 1177
18 Boxes 12 standard, 6 custom
The Butler mss., 1835-1937, includes papers, 1877-1937, of Amos William Butler, 1860-1937, zoologist, anthropologist, and sociologist, and a few papers, 1835-1871, of his father, William Wallace Butler, 1810-1903, merchant and farmer.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Career of William Wallace Butler: born, Brookville, Indiana, March 11, 1810, the son of Amos Butler, 1770-1837, and Mary (Wallace) Butler, 1786-1852; moved with parents to Hanover, Indiana, attended Hanover College; returned to Brookville, 1832; started a general mercantile business, 1835; disposed of goods and devoted himself to superintending his farms and other business, 1842; married three times; son, Amos William Butler, child of third marriage; died November 21, 1903.
Career of Amos William Butler: born, Brookville, Indiana, October 1, 1860, the son of William Wallace Butler and Hannah (Wright) Butler; educated in Brookville schools, including a year or more at Brookville College; attended Hanover College; spent winter, 1879-1880, in Mexico, nominally attached to U.S. legation at Mexico City but actually engaged in field work in zoology and archaeology; before completing education spent several years in insurance business in Brookville, Indiana; married Mary I. Reynolds of Brookville, June 2, 1880; a founder of the Brookville Society of Natural History, 1881; a founder of the Indiana Academy of Science, 1885; A.B., Indiana University, 1894; president, Indiana Academy of Science, 1895; ornithologist, Department of Geology and Resources of Indiana, 1896-1897; secretary, Indiana Board of State Charities, 1898-1923; a founder of Indiana Audubon Society, 1898; president of Indiana State Truancy Board, 1898-1912, secretary, 1913-1921; A.M., Indiana University, 1900; a founder of American Anthropological Association, 1902; lecturer on economics, Purdue University, 1905; later lectured on public charities at Purdue, Indiana University, the University of Chicago, the Lane Theological Seminary, and the Chicago School of Philanthropy; president of National Conference of Charities and Corrections, 1906-1907; member of White House children's conference, 1909; president of American Prison Association, 1909-1910; chairman of American Committee on the International Prison Congress, Washington, D.C., 1910; LLD, Hanover College, 1915; Ph.D., Butler University, 1915; president of Indiana Conference of Charities and Corrections, 1915; secretary of Indiana Commission on Mental Defectives, 1915; delegate to 2nd Pan American Scientific Congress, Washington, D.C., 1915-1916; a founder of the Society of Indiana Pioneers, 1916; chairman of executive committee of Indiana Society for Mental Hygiene, 1918-1925; a founder of the American Mammalogists, 1919; LLD, Indiana University, 1922; delegate from the U.S. to the International Prison Congress, London, 1925; president of Indiana Society for Mental Hygiene, 1925-1930; senior sociologist, U.S. Bureau of Efficiency to advise the Congressional committee on Federal Penal and Reformatory Institutions, 1928-1929; member of Advisory Committee to President Hoover's National Committee on Law Observance and Enforcement, 1929-1931; secretary of Indiana Committee on Observance and Enforcement of Law, 1929-1931; a founder of the International Commission on Mental Hygiene, and a member of the 1st International Congress on Mental Hygiene, Washington, D.C., 1930; delegate from the U.S. to the International Prison Congress, Prague, 1930; member of the executive board of the American Institute of Criminal Law and Criminology, 1935; member American Ornithologists' Union; and fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science.
Biographical data from Marcus Ward Lyon, Jr., Amos William Butler, Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science, XLVII: 21-25, 1937; B.W. Evermann, Amos William Butler, Audubon Year Book of the Indiana Audubon Society, 1932, pp. 5-19.
Lists of Butler's numerous writings appear in the Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science, XLVII: 25-30, 1937, and in the Audubon Year Book of the Indiana Audubon Society, 1932, pp. 5-19.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Wallace Butler in the collection consist of the indentures, tax receipts, a subscription for the erection of a Presbyterian church in the town of Brookville, Indiana, March 29, 1848; Franklin County, Indiana Bible Society, Report of a committee appointed to examine the accounts of the society, April 1852; and notes for a History of Presbyterianism in and about Brookville, Indiana by Ludlow D. Potter, 1852.
The papers of Amos William Butler from 1877-1888 deal almost entirely with zoological subjects, particularly birds. The later years of the collection also contain material on these subjects, but from 1889 on the bulk of the papers relate to charities and corrections, including material on prisons, reformatories, parole, probation, insanity, feeble-mindedness, mental hygiene, orphanages, child welfare, the blind, etc.; the work of the Indiana Board of state charities; notes on Indiana and other U.S. institutions of charities and corrections; meetings of the International Prison Congress, American Prison Association, the National Conference of Charities and Corrections, and the National Commission on Law Observance and Enforcement, and the Indiana Society for Mental Hygiene, the Indiana State Conference of Charities and Corrections, and the Indiana Committee on Observance and Enforcement of Law. The collection also contains papers on: the early history of Brookville, Indiana; Hanover College; and various other societies of which Butler was a member, among them being the Brookville Society of Natural History; the Indiana Academy of Science, 1886-1936; the Indiana Audubon Society, 1907-1930; the Society of Indiana Pioneers; and the World Peace Foundation.
Photographs include pictures of Amos William Butler and members of his family, Florida, particularly New Smyrna and vicinity, and Aztec remains in Mexico. There are also clippings, 1885-1937; printed materials on charities and corrections and related subjects, scientific societies, the Irvington Presbyterian church of Indianapolis, Indiana, and universities; and four scrapbooks, 1907-1908, 1910, and 1923-1927, containing pictures, programs, clippings, pamphlets, and maps.
Note on Indexing Term - "International relations": Later in life Butler became deeply involved with social reform and included in his papers is material pertaining to the World Peace Foundation in Boston.
Acquisition Information
Acquired 1939-1940
Birds--Colorado.; Birds--Indiana.; Birds--Mexico.; Presbyterians--Indiana.; Mental illness--Indiana.; Mammals--Indiana.; Psychiatric hospitals--Indiana.; Reformatories--Indiana.; International relations; Brookville (Ind.)--History.; Medicine; Science; Butler, Amos W. (Amos William), 1860-1937--Correspondence.; American Peace Society.; Brookville Society of Natural History (Brookville, Ind.); Franklin County Bible Society.; Hanover College--History.; Indiana Academy of Science.; Indiana Audubon Society.; Indiana Society for Mental Hygiene.; Indiana State Conference on Social Work.; Society of Indiana Pioneers.; World Peace Foundation.
- Materials relating to Butler family (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Included in the collection are letters from the following prominent persons:
  Edith Abbott
  Grace Abbott
  Russell Bigelow Abbott
  William Louis Abbott
  John Alfred McDowell Adair
  Alva Adams
  John Ottis Adams
  Robert Judson Aley
  Joel Asaph Allen
  William Harvey Allen
  Frederic Almy
  Martin Frederick Ansel
  John J. Appel
  Joseph Charles Arthur
  Charles Albert Ashburner
  Sir Allen Bristol Aylesworth
  Albion (Fellows) Bacon
  Liberty Hyde Bailey
  Joshua L. Baily
  Harry Foster Bain
  Spencer Fullerton Baird
  Albert Baker
  Harry Everett Barnard
  Charles Reid Barnes
  Henry A. Barnhart
  Kate (Waller) Barrett
  Katharine Isabel (Hayes) Barrows
  Samuel June Barrows
  William James Beal
  Charles Emerson Beecher
  Charles August Behrens
  Robert Bell
  August Belmont
  Frank Williamson Benson
  Charles Bernstein
  Charles Edwin Bessey
  Union Noble Bethell
  Albert Jeremiah Beveridge
  Ernest Percy Bicknell
  Theodore Gilmore Bilbo
  Frank Billings
  Frank Wilson Blackmar
  Eliza Ann (Cooper) Blaker
  William Martin Blanchard
  Willis Stanley Blatchley
  Charles Harvey Bollman
  Charles Joseph Bonaparte
  Charles A. Bookwalter
  Maud (Charlesworth) Booth
  Eugène Borel
  Claude Gernade Bowers
  Paul Eugene Bowers
  David Ross Boyd
  John Joseph Boylan
  Jeffrey Richardson Brackett
  James Henry Brady
  John Casper Branner
  William Brewster
  Daniel Garrison Brinton
  Zebulon Reed Brockway
  Bryant Butler Brooks
  Demarchus Clariton Brown
  Henry Baker Brown
  Herbert Daniel Brown
  Hilton Ultimus Brown
  John A. Brown
  Joseph Mackey Brown
  Henry Lane Bruner
  William Jennings Bryan
  William Lowe Bryan
  Albert G. Bryant
  Henry Augustus Buchtel
  James Monroe Buckley
  John Burke
  Bailey Barton Burritt
  Noble Chase Butler
  Joseph Perkins Byers
  Starr Cadwallader
  Charles Macfie Campbell
  John TenBrook Campbell
  Joseph Maull Carey
  Henry Smith Carhart
  Charles Arthur Carlisle
  Alexander Mitchell Carroll
  Christian Carl Carstens
  Hamilton Cassels
  Demetrio Castillo Duany
  Sidney Johnston Catts
  John William Cavanaugh
  Arthur Billings Chaffee
  Montague Chamberlain
  Joseph Chartrand
  Charles Lionel Chute
  George Washington Clarke
  Grace Giddings (Julian) Clarke
  James Everitt Clarke
  Edward Nicholas Clopper
  Ewing Cockrell
  Charles Fisher Coffin
  Lotus Delta Coffman
  Wilbur Adelman Cogshall
  John Rogers Commons
  John Heman Converse
  Melville Thurston Cook
  Mary Elizabeth Burroughs (Roberts) Coolidge
  John Gordon Cooper
  Edward Drinker Cope
  Owen Copp
  John Jacob Cornwell
  Elliott Coues
  John Merle Coulter
  Stanley Coulter
  William Chalmers Covert
  Edward Travers Cox
  James Middleton Cox
  Joseph M. Cravens
  Edgar Roscoe Cumings
  Oscar Kennedy Cushing
  James Elbert Cutler
  Mabel (Potter) Daggett
  Charles Benedict Davenport
  Katharine Bement Davis
  Albert Eugene Davisson
  George Bannerman Dealey
  Charles Clemons Deam
  Sarah S. (Platt) Decker
  Charles A. DeCourcy
  Robert Weeks DeForest
  Charles Samuel Deneen
  David Worth Dennis
  William Cullen Dennis
  Edward Thomas Devine
  John Hibbett DeWitt
  Solomon Cravens Dickey
  Lincoln Dixon
  James Owen Dorsey
  Hugh Dougherty
  Eben Sumner Draper
  William Francis Drewry
  Charles Redway Wilmarth Dryer
  Knight Dunlap
  Jacob Piatt Dunn
  Edward Fitzsimons Dunne
  Winfield Taylor Durbin
  Charles Dury
  John Samuel Duss
  William Dutcher
  Edwin T. Earl
  Walter Evans Edge
  John Joy Edson
  David Morton Edwards
  Edward Eggleston
  Carl H. Eigenmann
  Edward Charles Elliott
  Alston Ellis
  William John Ellis
  Thomas Emmet Ellison
  Charles Abram Ellwood
  Edson James Emerick
  Charles Phillips Emerson
  Haven Emerson
  Barton Warren Evermann
  Charles Warren Fairbanks
  Leon Charles Faulkner
  Walter Elmore Fernald
  Woodbridge Nathan Ferris
  Frank Albert Fetter
  Morris M. Feuerlicht
  Jesse Walter Fewkes
  James Louis Fieser
  Tom Finty
  Daniel Webster Fisher
  Duncan Upshaw Fletcher
  Bernard Flexner
  Arthur Lee Foley
  Homer Folks
  Stephen Alfred Forbes
  John Franklin Fort
  William Fortune
  Eugene Noble Foss
  Warren William Foster
  William Dudley Foulke
  Lee Kaufer Frankel
  Berthold Freudenthal
  Ray Clarence Friesner
  Simon Henry Gage
  Harry Otto Garman
  James Wilford Garner
  John Hutchison Garnier
  Francis Henry Gavisk
  Enrico Hillyer Giglioli
  Charles Henry Gilbert
  Albert Waller Gilchrist
  John Lewis Gillin
  William Ellsworth Glasscock
  Wenzeslaus Karl Maximilian Maria^graf von Gleispach
  John Mark Glenn
  Mary (Willcox) Glenn
  George Brown Goode
  James Putnam Goodrich
  William Freeman Myrick Goss
  William C. Graves
  James Leon Greene
  John Hubert Greusel
  John Hugo Grimm
  George Richmond Grose
  Julia Henrietta Gulliver
  Carl Gunderson
  Carl Eugen Guthe
  James Edward Hagerty
  Matthias Loring Haines
  Horatio Hale
  Allen Garland Hall
  Edward Richardson Hall
  Frederic Aldin Hall
  Matthew Walton Hall
  Charles Wesley Hargitt
  Judson Harmon
  Abram Winegardner Harris
  Hastings Hornell Hart
  Henry Drury Hatfield
  Marion E. Hay
  Oliver Perry Hay
  William Harrison Hays
  James Alexander Hemenway
  Charles Richmond Henderson
  Walter Cleaveland Henderson
  William Elmer Henry
  Henry Wetherbee Henshaw
  William Howard Hickman
  Linnaeus Neal Hines
  Frederick Webb Hodge
  Nathaniel Dana Carlile Hodges
  Enoch George Hogate
  James Irving Holcomb
  Louis Edward Holden
  John Hampden Holliday
  William Steele Holman
  Carl Oliver Holmes
  Harry Nicholls Holmes
  William Henry Holmes
  Ben W. Hooper
  Herbert Hoover
  William Temple Hornaday
  Leland Ossian Howard
  Thomas Carr Howe
  Aleš Hrdlicka
  Charles Evans Hughes
  Edwin Holt Hughes
  William St. Pierre Hughes
  George Wylie Paul Hunt
  Huber William Hurt
  John Newell Hurty
  Henry Augustus Huston
  Harry Burns Hutchins
  John Ireland
  William Glanton Irwin
  James Frederick Jackson
  Edmund Janes James
  Joseph Francis James
  Joseph Jastrow
  Oliver Peebles Jenkins
  Jeremiah Whipple Jenks
  Richard Henry Jesse
  John Price Durbin John
  Alexander Johnson
  Charles Henry Johnson
  John Albert Johnson
  James A. Johnston
  Lynds Jones
  David Starr Jordan
  James Yadkin Joyner
  Arthur Piper Kellogg
  John Harvey Kellogg
  Paul Underwood Kellogg
  Robert Lincoln Kelly
  Carl Kelsey
  Calvin Noyes Kendall
  William Converse Kendall
  Charles Kettleborough
  Alfred Vincent Kidder
  Edward Martin Kindle
  Harry Andrews King
  Henry Churchill King
  John Sterling Kingsley
  La Vega George Kinne
  George Hughes Kirby
  William Walton Kitchin
  Rufus Bernard von Kleinsmid
  George Milton Kline
  John Koren
  William Frederick Kuhn
  George Frederick Kunz
  James Sansome Lakin
  Ricardo R. Lancis
  Julia Clifford Lathrop
  Harry Hamilton Laughlin
  Lewis E. Lawes
  George Newbold Lawrence
  Porter Raymond Lee
  Frederick William Lehmann
  Harry Guyer Leslie
  Frank Leverett
  Orlando Faulkland Lewis
  Charles Freeman Libby
  Richard Lieber
  Harlow Lindley
  Samuel McCune Lindsay
  Benjamin Barr Lindsey
  Burton Edward Livingston
  John Uri Lloyd
  George Browning Lockwood
  William Newton Logan
  William Frederick Lorenz
  Owen Reed Lovejoy
  Frank Orren Lowden
  Frederick Elmore Lumley
  Charles Jackson Lynn
  Frank Emory Lyon
  Robert Wesley McBride
  Robert Wilson McClaughry
  James Gore King McClure
  Warren Terry McCray
  James Bennett McCreary
  George Grant MacCurdy
  Daniel Trembly MacDougal
  Sir Alexander Burness McHardy
  Thomas McIlwraith
  Roderick Duncan McKenzie
  William McKibben
  Paul Vories McNutt
  William Henry McReynolds
  Frank LeRond McVey
  Henry Brown Floyd Macfarland
  Julian William Mack
  George Lewis Mackintosh
  Elliott Woolfolk Major
  Sir James Marchant
  Thomas Riley Marshall
  Otis Tufton Mason
  Edwin Doak Mead
  Carl Leo Mees
  Thomas Corwin Mendenhall
  Charles Oliver Merica
  Clinton Hart Merriam
  James Cushing Merrill
  Carl Elias Milliken
  William Alfred Millis
  Frederick H. Mills
  William C. Mills
  William Joseph Mills
  William DeWitt Mitchell
  William J. Moenkhaus
  Clarence Bloomfield Moore
  David Richard Moore
  George Thomas Moore
  Henry Frank Moore
  John Bassett Moore
  Richard Bishop Moore
  Charles Washington Moores
  Merrill Moores
  Ephraim Franklin Morgan
  David Myers Mottier
  William Henry Moyer
  Burton Dorr Myers
  Quincy Alden Myers
  John Ulric Nef
  Edward William Nelson
  Nels Christian Nelson
  Harry Stewart New
  George T. Nicholson
  Timothy Nicholson
  Edmund Favor Noel
  Frank Parson Norbury
  Edwin Lee Norris
  Cecil Clare North
  Cyrus Northrop
  Thomas Herbert Norton
  William Albert Noyes
  Wallace George Nye
  Harry Church Oberholser
  William Henry O'Connell
  Howard Washington Odum
  Edward Orton
  Henry Leslie Osborn
  Herbert Osborn
  Edward William Osborne
  Winfred Overholser
  Richard Owen
  Robert Latham Owen
  Garfield Bromley Oxnam
  Theodore Sherman Palmer
  Albert George Parker
  Benjamin Strattan Parker
  David Maclean Parry
  William Wood Parsons
  Thomas Gilbert Pearson
  Stanton Judkins Peelle
  Paul Skeels Peirce
  Frederick Peterson
  Sir William Peterson
  Charles Winfield Pilgrim
  Merritt Willis Pinckney
  Lemuel Arthur Pittenger
  Walter George Hepburne-Scott
  9th baron Polwarth
  Aram J. Pothier
  George Herbert Prouty
  Albert Homer Purdue
  Frederic Ward Putnam
  Kate (Milner) Rabb
  Samuel Moffett Ralston
  Frank Lange Randall
  Leo M. Rappaport
  James Bronson Reynolds
  John Merriman Reynolds
  Mary Ellen Richmond
  Robert Ridgway
  Charles Valentine Riley
  Thomas James Riley
  George Lucas Roberts
  James Alexander Robertson
  Gifford Simeon Robinson
  James Jaquess Robinson
  Arthur Curtis Rogers
  Theodore Roosevelt
  Joseph Nelson Rose
  Victor Rosewater
  Edward Alsworth Ross
  Leonard August Rossing
  David Andrew Rothrock
  Leo S. Rowe
  Sir Evelyn John Ruggles-Brise
  Frank Russell
  Robert Lemuel Sackett
  John Hall Sage
  Thomas William Salmon
  Franklin Benjamin Sanborn
  Jared Young Sanders
  Kenosha Sessions
  Thomas Roerty Shipp
  George H. Simmons
  Harold Douglas Singer
  Hubert Marshall Skinner
  William Frederick Slocum
  Alexander Smith
  Bolton Smith
  Eugene Allen Smith
  Hugh McCormick Smith
  Samuel Edwin Smith
  Jonathan Le Moyne Snyder
  John J. Sonsteby
  John Wesley Spencer
  William Jasper Spillman
  Mary Angela Spink
  Alfred Springer
  Frederick Starr
  Theodore Clement Steele
  Joseph Beal Steere
  Leonard Stejneger
  Frank Mann Stewart
  William Rhinelander Stewart
  John B. Stoll
  Winthrop Ellsworth Stone
  Witmer Stone
  Albert Boynton Storms
  Elmer William Stout
  Thomas Nelson Strong
  Francis Sumichrast
  Walter Taylor Sumner
  Joseph Swain
  Henry Chapman Swearingen
  Glen Levin Swiggett
  William Howard Taft
  Thomas Taggart
  Graham Taylor
  Mark Thislethwaite
  Cyrus Thomas
  Mason Blanchard Thomas
  Julia Alice (Conner) Thompson
  William Oxley Thompson
  Craig Sharpe Thoms
  Allen Benton Thrasher
  Henry Winfred Thurston
  Francis J. Torrance
  Arthur Whittlesey Towne
  William Trelease
  Frederick William True
  Joseph Patrick Tumulty
  David Turpie
  Millard Evelyn Tydings
  Albert Brennus Ulrey
  Henry Elias Van Deman
  George Vaux
  Monroe Vayhinger
  Chester Garfield Vernier
  Robert Scadden Vessey
  George Edgar Vincent
  Oscar McMurtrie Voorhees
  Charles Gray Wagner
  Charles Doolittle Walcott
  Clarence Abiathar Waldo
  Henry Baldwin Ward
  Eugene Fitch Ware
  Fred Maltby Warner
  Henry Kimball Warren
  Frederic Leonard Washburn
  James Eli Watson
  Arthur Trezevant Wayne
  Ulysses Grant Weatherly
  Francis Marion Webster
  David Fairchild Weeks
  William Henry Welch
  James Edward West
  F.D. Whipp
  Charles Abiathar White
  Reuel Clyde White
  Thomas Bruce White
  Ernest Stagg Whitin
  George Woodward Wickersham
  Frank Scott Corey Wicks
  John Henry Wigmore
  Ansley Wilcox
  Harvey Washington Wiley
  Sidney Dean Wilgus
  Mornay Williams
  Augustus Everett Willson
  George Smith Wilson
  Harry Bruce Wilson
  Newton Horace Winchell
  Frederick Howard Wines
  Charles Francis Winter
  William Albert Wirt
  William Niles Wishard
  Clark Wissler
  Robert Henry Wolcott
  James Albert Woodburn
  Robert Archey Woods
  Walter Carleton Woodward
  William Watson Woollen
  Theophilus Adam Wylie
  Elbert Robb Zaring
  Consult the Manuscripts Index in the Library for dates of letters of individual correspondents.
  - Correspondence, 1835-1897; (31 folders) (Box 1)
    Includes:
    Natural history notes, 1884-1892 (1 folder)
    Notes of visits-Eastern hospital, 1891 (1 folder)
    Notes of visits-Soldiers and sailors orphans home, 1891-1914 (1 folder)
    Natural history notes, 1893-1897 (1 folder, 1 notebook)
    Notes of visits-State prison, 1894-1916 (1 folder, 6 notebooks)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1909, Oct. 15; (31 folders) (Box 2)
    Notes of visits - Reformatory, 1902-1914 (1 folder)
    Notes of visits - School for Deaf, 1904 (1 folder)
    Notes of visits - Soldiers' Home, 1904 (1 folder)
  - Correspondence, 1909, Oct. 16-1913, Aug.; (26 folders) (Box 3)
    R.S.V.P cards for Indiana Academy of Science banquet, Nov. 26, 1909 (1 envelope)
    Ticket stubs for Indiana Academy of Science banquet, Nov. 26, 1909 (1 envelope)
  - Correspondence, 1913, Sept.-1917, Dec.; (25 folders) (Box 4)
    Mental Defectives in Indiana, 1916, Nov. 10; Indiana, A Century of Progress: A Study of the Development of Public Charities and Correction, 1790-1915, 1916; Survey of the Mentally Diseased and Defective in Indiana, for the National Committee for Mental Hygiene, 1917 (1 vol.)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1922; (20 folders) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1922, July-1925, June; (60 folders) (Box 6)
    Tributes to Amos William Butler, 1922 (1 folder)
  - Correspondence, 1925, July-1929, July; (27 folders) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1929, Aug.-1937; (27 folders) (Box 8)
    Proceedings at Conference of Committee on Observance and Enforcement of Law, Apr. 26, 1930
    Indiana Committee on Observance and Enforcement of Law. Conference, July 26, 1930
    Report of the Advisory Committee on Penal Institutions, Probation and Parole, 1931
    Balance sheet, treasurer's report, and auditor's certificate for Hanover College, Apr.-May 1932
  - Charities, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - Charities and corrections, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - Photographs (Box 9)
  - Amos William Butler (Box 9)
  - Florida, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Brookville, Indiana - History (Box 9)
  - Florida (Box 9)
  - Indiana Academy of Science (Box 9)
  - Mexico (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Scientific Papers (Box 9)
  - Prisons, (5 folders) (Box 9)
  - Prisons, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Clippings, 1885-1934; (18 folders) (Box 10)
  - Clippings, 1935-1937; (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Printed (Box 11)
  - Indiana Board of Charities and State Board of Control (Box 11)
  - Charities and Corrections, Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Child welfare. Eugenics (Box 11)
  - Drug addiction (Box 11)
  - Mental defectives (Box 11)
  - Mental hygiene societies (Box 11)
  - Poor relief in Indiana (Box 11)
  - Psychiatry and the courts (Box 11)
  - Statistics, surveys, and reports on prisons (Box 11)
  - Senate and House bills (Box 11)
  - Rules and forms pertaining to penal institutions (Box 11)
  - Prison forms (Box 11)
  - Probation material (Box 11)
  - Prison associations (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous. Prison material (Box 11)
  - Printed (Box 12)
  - Irvington Presbyterian Church (Box 12)
  - Scientific societies (Box 12)
  - Universities (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1907-1908 (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1910 (Oversize 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1910 (Oversize 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1922 (Oversize 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1923-1927 (Oversize 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Oversize 6)
    Bird sighting charts, 1895; prisoners' bill of fare, Indiana State Prison, Aug. 6 and 13, 1904; roll of the House of Representatives, Mar. 4 and 5, 1921; Reception Committee, listed by Indiana county, undated